we all know radar is a way of detecting distant objects
we also know it uses energy to do this
but how exactly does it work
what kind of things can be done
with Radar to make it useful
with modern computers to process Radar results
we can do a lot like look at weather patterns
or find distant objects in the air
or even in space
but before we go into that
i thought it would be a good idea to get a basic
understanding of how Radar waves work first
so let's dive in
at its core  Radar works on the principle that radio
waves are reflected off of objects
some materials are especially
reflective to these radio waves
like most metals
but just about everything can
reflect these waves to some degree
this means it's possible to illuminate a distant
surface with radio waves and see it just like if
you were shining a big searchlight on it  in fact
if you think of Radar like a searchlight
it'll help in understanding its properties
because Radar waves share a lot in common with light
so far you've heard me use radar and
radio waves interchangeably
that's because they're exactly the same
they're both electromagnetic waves
the only difference is how they're used
in fact the waves generated by a
microwave oven are also the same
this was something discovered by Percy
Spencer in the nineteen forties
who noticed a chocolate bar in his pocket melted while
he was working on a radar emitter for the military
he would later go on to patent the microwave oven
those same electromagnetic waves can
be used for different purposes
so let's take a look at how they're generated
whether you're transmitting a radio broadcast or a
radar signal one of the easiest ways to do it is with
a simple antenna like this monopole antenna
when you run an electrical current up this antenna
it will radiate electromagnetic waves
that follow the current upward
then if you reverse the polarity
the same will happen in the opposite direction
if you keep doing this
then you'll generate a pattern with peaks and troughs
these waves appear with the frequency that
matches how fast you're switching the polarity
we measure that frequency by counting how many
times a wave passes a point in space per second
one wave per second is one hertz
and a million waves per second is one megahertz
the size of the antenna also affects how well
it broadcasts or receives these waves
most modern Radar systems will use a component
called a magnetron to generate these radar waves
instead of a simple monopole antenna
the waves it creates are exactly the same and
just like a monopole the size matters
the volume of these cavities determines
the wavelength of the emitted waves
when we talk about Radar reflections what's
actually happening is the Radar imparts an
electrical current on a surface it comes into contact with
then as that charge moves along the surface it
generates a new wave just like our transmitting antenna
we'll dive into this a little deeper in a future video
for now we want to focus on the waves themselves
all Radar waves have an electrical
component and a magnetic component
which is why they're also called electromagnetic waves
you'll always find these fields at
ninety degrees to each other
and the direction the electrical field
faces is called its polarization
in this case it's vertically polarized since
the electric field is oriented up and down
but if it were rotated ninety degrees
it would be horizontally polarized
since all em waves travel at the same speed which is just
below the speed of light within the earth's atmosphere
then changing the frequency of these waves
also affects how far apart each peak is
that distance is known as the wavelength
at three hundred megahertz the wavelength is one meter
and at three hundred kilohertz it's one kilometer
so we can see that as frequency goes up
wavelength goes down
it's important to know about frequency and
wavelength because Radar waves interact with the
world differently depending on the length of the wave
em frequencies are organized in groups called bands
there are different naming
conventions out there for these bands
but two of the more popular ones
are from the IEEE and nato
this first scale was created in World War II
to give names for radar frequencies  later on
nato would create this second scale which makes it a little
more intuitive to identify the frequency at a glance
lower frequencies are less affected by
weather than higher frequencies
fog and rain absorb Radar energy and weaken its power
that's because the wavelengths of higher frequencies
are closer in size to raindrops and water particles
which means they interact with them more closely
here we can see that these lower bands have much
lower attenuation than the higher bands
below about three gigahertz there isn't much effect
so when these frequencies are transmitting in bad weather
they're more likely to get through
but even in clear weather
we see that the higher frequencies are
heavily attenuated just by the atmosphere
so less of their power will make it
through at longer distances
once you get to the really high frequencies
their range can be as short as a few meters
looking at this chart
you may be wondering then why would
we ever use higher frequencies
to answer that we need to look at how
our waves travel through the air
here we can see another antenna
in this case it's a dipole because it has two ends as
opposed to a single one like the monopole we looked at
earlier  as our antenna radiates we see that
the waves aren't two dimensional
为什么呢
因为当我们增加频率时
波长会收缩
当我们减少频率时
波长会增长
when we get a return echo from one of these big bubbles
we don't actually get much information
besides the fact that there was something
reflective somewhere inside that bubble
so if that wave was a mile wide
then that could be anywhere within a
mile wide segment of the world
that might be enough to get a rough
idea of where an aircraft is
but not enough to get good precision on it
的莱克如果你需要它
引导导弹
朝着它或者如果你想
要识别它
通过它的形状
更高的频率
产生更小的波
这会给你
更好的分辨率
it's just like how higher resolution on a
monitor gives you smaller pixels on the screen
this resolution is called angular resolution
when we're talking about the
equivalent of pixels in your radar
we mean how wide those pixels are in azimuth
this is important because if multiple objects appear inside
one of those resolution cells like aircraft flying in close
formation then they'll appear as just a single return
but as we discussed earlier this extra
resolution comes at the cost of range
there's also another factor that
affects the range of radar detection
as energy radiates away from the emitter
it spreads out over a wider area the
further it gets from the emitter
it looks like this
let's say we have a hypothetical
radar with nine Watts of power
and each watt is represented by a red line
at a certain range
all nine Watts fit into this square of space
but when we go out to twice that range
those nine Watts are now spread across a volume
that covers four of those same size squares
so each square gets only two or three Watts of radar energy
now if we go out even further to three times that range
now we see that a volume of nine
squares is still getting energy
but none of those squares is
receiving more than one watt of energy
the same holds true for reflected energy
it'll get scattered and weaker on the way back
so if this radar station needed a
minimum of one watt to see a target
then it would only be able to detect targets
in this region between ranges one and two
but this radar energy out here doesn't just vanish
it can still be received by other sources
even if the emitter can't do much with it
let's take a look at an example
here we have two fighter jets
pointing their radars at each other
but this mig twenty nine doesn't have
a return yet on the f sixteen
because it's too far away to receive the
minimum amount of power for detection
however from the f sixteen's point of view we can see that
it is receiving a Radar signal from the米格29
in this case the f sixteen pilot has received some
useful information from the米格二十九's Radar
even though the米格29 still hasn't
gotten any meaningful returns
this dilution of power is known as an inverse
square law and it affects all radiated energy
another factor that affects range is
specific to low frequency radars
at these lower frequencies radar waves are
reflected by the layer of ionized air in the
atmosphere known as the ionosphere
so they can travel over terrain that would
otherwise block the signal and reflect back
from objects at an even longer distance
they can also bounce up off the surface and may
potentially interfere with return echoes
these extra returns are known as multipath echoes
and they can cause ghosts to appear in a pattern like this
so it's something that builders and operators
of radar systems need to account for
these lower frequencies can also be deflected
around obstacles because of their long wavelength
this phenomenon is known as a ground wave
and it also allows these signals to travel farther
you'll find high frequency radars in aircraft and missiles
not just because of the issue with low frequencies
but because of antenna size
low frequency radars have a high wavelength
so they need larger antennas that may not easily
fit into the nose of a fighter or a missile
but they aren't problem free
high frequency radars are stopped by
obstacles like manmade structures and terrain
this means that after a certain distance
the curvature of the earth
actually blocks the radar signal
let's take a look at an example of this
if a Radar system is at a height of twenty feet and is
searching for an aircraft at an altitude of five thousand
feet  then it will have a line of sight on that
aircraft at eighty nautical miles
anything flying below this aircraft will
be hidden away in this radar shadow
what if that same aircraft was flying
at two hundred and fifty feet
it wouldn't emerge from the radar shadow
until twenty one point five nautical miles
that's almost sixty miles closer
so you can see why low level tactics are popular
among military pilots that want to elude radar
of course increasing the height of
the Radar changes the equation
if we lift that radar up to twenty thousand feet
it can now see that low flying plane at
one hundred sixty seven nautical miles
this is why awacs aircraft are such a powerful asset
so far we've talked about the
properties of different Radar frequencies
but we haven't gone over how those Radar waves are
turned into useful information for a Radar operator
there are a few things we can do to make
our radar emissions more useful
for example
with this emission pattern
we could get a reflection on an object here
which we could capture with the receiver antenna here
but this arrangement would give us a problem
all we would see on our receiver is a spike in energy
and that spike would look exactly the same
if it came from an object that was here
or even here
so we need a way to shape our Radar wave
so we don't cover such a wide area
a common way of doing this is with a
directional antenna like a dish
this way we can steer our energy
and if we get a return
then we know the azimuth to that return
but this method isn't perfect
because radar travels in waves it doesn't
stick to a neat straight line pattern
some of that energy goes off to the side and even
behind the emitter in a pattern that looks like this
this main cone is known as the main lobe
these smaller offshoots are side lobes
and anything behind the emitter is a back lobe
we have to be careful with these because
they can give us returns we may not want
this radiation pattern also presents another challenge
as it scans its surroundings
it'll pick up aircraft within its main and side lobes
but there's going to be a gap in
coverage above the Radar site itself
because this area is shaped like an inverted cone
it's known as the cone of silence
any aircraft overflying the radar
won't show up for the operator
so it's common to see radars deployed with overlapping
coverage to take care of each other's blind spots
there's an additional problem with this setup
when we're continuously emitting waves like this
we only know the direction of a return
so we have to do something extra with our
emissions if we want to get additional data
like the range and speed of a target
there are some techniques to help with this
like pulsing radar emissions and measuring doppler shift
we'll go over both of these topics
as we continue this series
the ultimate goal here is to explain the
fundamentals of Ew in modern air combat
so later on we'll go over different methods for
countering detection like stealth and jamming
and we'll also talk about howIFF lets us identify aircraft
1st we'll need to understand how radars work which is
why we're covering that in the first few videos
i hope you found this useful and thanks for watching